Well, good morning, Canvas Church.
Thanks so much for joining us.
Thanks for worshiping with us this morning.
Donna, thanks for preparing on our hearts.
Super thankful for all that God has done in Christ for us.
This morning, we have one week between the end of our series through the book of James.
Let me introduce myself first.
For those of you that don't know me yet, if you're new here, my name is Ryan.
I'm one of the pastors here.
I'm so glad that you have joined us.
Last week, we finished up a series on the book of James.
Dave did an excellently long job.
He told me I owe you guys a few minutes, so I'm going to try and end.
I think he's watching online.
Dave, I love you.
We finished up the series through the book of James, and we have our outdoor service next Sunday.
After that, we're starting a series through the spiritual fruits that we're calling Summer Fruit because we're creative and catchy.
That's the only reason we called it that.
No, but I'm excited about that series.
I had one week in between the end of James and our series coming up on spiritual fruits.
If I'm honest, stand-alone messages, I really struggle with having freedom to pick what I'm going to talk about because as a communicator of the Scriptures,
I know that there's a temptation to pull out my soapbox and stand on the things that are important to me and talk about the things that I want to talk about rather than letting God speak to us.
And that's why I love talking through books of the Bible, talking through chapters of the Bible, because we kind of let God be the primary communicator.
And so I was really wrestling this week of like, man, don't insert yourself into the pulpit this week.
Like, what do we need to hear from God?
And as I was thinking about the spiritual fruits series, really there was one word, one topic that isn't going to be covered in the spiritual fruit series that I think is really crucial,
really central to the Christian faith, and that word is humility.
And so after some prayer and thinking, knowing I only had one week, what is something that's primary, central to the Christian faith,
something that we really need to hear about?
And I thought about the word humility, which led me to this passage in Philippians chapter 2,
which some of you that grew up in church are probably familiar with a famous passage about the humility of Jesus to come to earth,
to lay down his life, to sacrificially serve his creation, to draw us to himself.
And so that's where we're going to spend our time this morning.
And the main idea that I'm drawing from that text is this.
I believe that Paul is going to share with us from that text that the successful Christian life and church are assembled with an attitude of humility.
The successful Christian life and church are assembled with the attitude of humility.
And I chose these words intentionally.
I chose the word successful, and I chose the word assembled on purpose.
And we'll get to assembled in a little bit.
But the reason I chose the word successful is because the book of Philippians is pretty unique compared to some of Paul's other letters in the Bible.
Honestly, most of Philippians is pretty encouraging and cheerful.
A lot of theologians call the book of Philippians the book of joy.
Paul's just, like, pumped about the church at Philippi.
He's pumped about the Christians at Philippi.
And if you're familiar with the Scriptures at all, you know a lot of Paul's letters.
He's kind of grumpy and calling out people for their sin, right?
He's like, hey, you guys are messing up here, here, here.
Like, here's what you need to correct.
Here's what you need to change.
Here's how you can get better.
And really, Paul doesn't do much of that at all in the book of Philippians, which kind of leads us to believe that the Philippian church was actually a pretty healthy church full of pretty healthy believers.
Like, they were getting it right.
And Paul was encouraged by the health of the individual believers, their relationship with Jesus, the success that they were having as a church.
And so the passage we're going to study this morning is the central passage of the book of Philippians.
And I think what Paul is doing is he's saying, listen, the reason that you're so successful as individual Christians and as a church is because of your humility.
I think he's reminding them to stay focused on this attitude that has allowed them to have the successful life and church that they've had up until this point.
They've had an attitude of humility.
But we all know, if we've been human long enough, we know that if we start to have success in anything, oftentimes we lose sight of the reason we had our success to be human.
We could lose sight of the fact that it's actually an attitude of humility and sacrificial service that got us to where we are, and we might start to ad-lib or take control of our success for ourselves.
And so I think Paul is centering his letter on the attitude of Christ's humility to remind the Philippian church to stay focused on the attitude of humility.
And I think we can kind of take that same charge for ourselves and say, man, if we're going to succeed in a life of following Jesus,
and if we're going to be a church that's successful in demonstrating the attitudes and love of Jesus to our city and to a watching world,
humility has to be at the primary point of our lives.
Let's not lose sight of what true Christian success looks like.
And so I was thinking of a way to illustrate this, of this idea of having success and then losing sight of what made you successful to begin with.
The Internet broke a few years ago with IHOP.
IHOP launched this thing on Twitter where they decided they were going to change their name to IHOB.
Does anybody remember this?
A few people remember this.
Twitter was, like, broken for a while because they didn't say anything about why they changed it to IHOB.
They just, like, changed it to IHOB.
And so then Twitter went nuts.
Everybody was like, why is IHOB IHOB?
This doesn't make any sense.
And they launched this massive marketing campaign where they said that they were going to start doing burgers.
The International House of Pancake was going to transition from breakfast to start making burgers.
And for those of you that are familiar with Twitter at all, you know that the Wendy's Twitter account is a troll account, right?
The Wendy's account loves to make fun of other businesses.
And so once IHOB announced that they were going to have burgers, I think I have a picture of it on the screen, maybe.
Wendy's tweeted, not really afraid of burgers from a place that decided pancakes were too hard.
And so this is a classic example of a company forgetting what made them successful, like losing sight of the thing that brought them the success that they had.
Their name was literally pancakes, right?
Like breakfast was the thing that they were known for.
But maybe they got a little bit too far out from their skis and decided they were going to try to do something different.
And I think if we're honest with ourselves, whenever we have success in anything, but specifically in our relationship with Jesus, success in the Christian life always comes from being close to Jesus.
Always comes from faith and trust in Jesus, allowing through the Holy Spirit to work out from us.
Like we're not successful because of anything we do.
We're successful because of God working through us.
But because we're human beings, sinful, fallen, broken human beings, oftentimes we see that success.
We see God working through us, producing fruit and doing things.
And then we, because we're humans, maybe take hold of the reins for a little bit and say, man, I'm pretty good at this Christian thing.
I'm pretty good at this ministry thing, whatever it might look like.
And Paul is saying, you're doing great, keep it up.
And the way that you keep it up is through humility.
You're looking to Jesus, continually taking your eyes back to Jesus.
There was another church that struggled to do this in Revelation, the church of Laodicea, this famous passage about the lukewarm church.
And John says, why are they lukewarm?
Because you forgot your former love.
You lost sight of the thing that made you successful to begin with.
The thing that made you successful to begin with was sitting in the love of God and allowing the love of God to pour out from you and through you.
So, I think Paul is saying here, look, success in the Christian life comes from looking to Jesus, following the example of Jesus.
He's going to say, having the same mind of Christ Jesus.
And then he's going to unpack this idea of humility.
So that's the outlines of this morning.
That's the direction we're going.
Does that sound good with everybody?
We're nine minutes in, and that's the intro.
So let me pray, and then I'll try and keep close to my promise, so I'll give you a few minutes back.
Father, we are so grateful for the example of Jesus, for the humility of Jesus, for the way in which he disregarded all of his power and authority and position.
And then, as God and creator of God, to come and be born a human being in the first century in a small town that most people have never heard of before.
To live a human being in the first century in a small town that most people have never heard of him being in the first century in a small town that most people have never heard of before.
And for the people in the first century in a small town that most people have never heard of him being in the first century in a small town that most people have never heard of him being in the first century in a small town that most people have never heard of before.
And until that day comes, God, you've called us to have the same mind, the same attitude as Christ Jesus, who didn't think about himself more highly than he ought to, but he laid himself down.
We have the same mind that we think of others as more important than ourselves.
And so, God, this is not something that comes naturally to us.
We need your Holy Spirit to challenge, convict, encourage, point us to you this morning.
Do that this morning for your glory and for our good.
In Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
Well, in a divided society, I don't know if you guys know this about our society divided.
There's lots of arguments about anything and everything.
I think we can almost all agree on one simple thing, and that is this, that assembling things that you buy is the worst.
Like, if you pay money for something and then you have to put it together yourself, that's like one of the absolute worst things that could ever happen.
And the last thing I had to assemble, my wife and I, we got a treadmill with stimulus money, you know?
I was just trying to stimulate the economy.
I was stuck in my house, so I bought a treadmill with the stimulus money, and, you know, it was just great all around.
But I guess I never had a treadmill before, and whenever you see treadmills, they just, like, exist like a treadmill.
So I thought, you buy a treadmill, you pick up a treadmill, you take it to your house, you put it in your house, it's a treadmill.
No, it has to be put together.
And to be honest, it's the closest to a divorce that I have ever come, setting up this treadmill.
I probably could have used a sermon on humility before, during, and after the process of setting up this treadmill.
It was difficult.
But we finally got it, like, seven or eight hours later.
It was midnight when we finished the treadmill.
And it's still not together, as it should be.
It's together enough that it works.
But there's some screws that are in places that they weren't supposed to be in, but they were already there.
And it was, like, step three.
And we were on step seven when we realized.
So, anyway, we finished it.
We made it happen.
But, if I'm honest, the one thing, the one thing that makes assembling things better now for me, I'm not handy at all, very bad at putting things together.
But I'm a visual learner.
So, nowadays, YouTube has, like, a tutorial video for everything.
Like, I don't know.
It's incredible.
Literally everything.
You type in any product on YouTube, and there's a tutorial video of somebody that has the product, holding the product, showing you how to make it work.
And so, that has a little bit alleviated the stress for me of assembling things.
And the reason that I share this story with you as we hop into Philippians chapter 2 is because Paul kind of draws out this idea of humility.
I think he kind of lays it out at the beginning with some general instructions.
Like, on paper, this is what humility looks like.
This is what you're supposed to do to be humble.
But then, just in case we would be confused, just in case we might get it wrong, he gives us kind of a tutorial video or a vivid picture of Christ doing it.
He shows us what it looks like to be humble by showing us a picture of Jesus.
And then, at the end, he tells us what the final product looks like.
When true humility is lived out, what is the end result?
There's nothing better than standing back and seeing the final product.
And so, as we unpack this statement that the successful Christian life and church are assembled with an attitude of humility,
we're going to break it down into those three parts.
It's the general instructions, the video tutorial or the picture of what that looks like, and then the end result.
So, the general instructions are found in chapter 2, verses 3 and 4.
Paul says,
Pretty basic, pretty simple instructions.
This is what Paul says, that those of you who are going to assemble your life with an attitude of humility, this is what your life should look like.
Don't be selfish.
Don't try to impress others.
Be humble.
Thinking of others as better than yourselves.
It's a pretty simple instruction, pretty basic instruction.
But, I mean, even when you assemble things, like, the engineers do a pretty good job of making the instructions as simple as possible,
but it's easy to read into things and question things.
And you're like, wait a second, does that mean this goes here and that goes there?
And I think the same can happen with our own prideful, selfish hearts.
We hear things like, don't be selfish.
Don't try and impress others.
And we're like, yeah, I get that.
But, what about in this situation?
Or what about in this circumstance?
Or what if this happens?
And we tend to get distracted by the basic instructions.
Essentially what Paul is saying here is he's saying, don't selfishly serve your own interests,
but instead selflessly serve the interests of others all the time.
That's the command.
That's how we live out this attitude of humility.
Don't selfishly serve your own interests, but instead selflessly serve the interests of others.
See, I think most of us, we like this idea.
We would agree with this attitude.
We like the idea of selflessly serving others.
We've all heard it said that it's better to give than to receive.
I think we all like the idea of selflessly serving others as long as it fits nicely into a few hours of our calendar
in between the majority of tasks that ultimately revolve around us.
Right?
Like selflessly, sacrificially serving other people.
We like the idea if it fits in a schedule that ultimately is built around our desires, our wants, our needs,
our family's desires, our family's wants, and their needs.
And if we're really honest, like we get like super transparent, sometimes even our willingness to serve others comes out of the selfish desire.
Even our own humility, like we feign humility in order to build this reputation where people think we're awesome,
where people think we're successful, where people think we're really crushing it as a Christian
because we selflessly sacrifice and serve others all the time.
And sometimes if we're really honest, the motivation of our hearts to do that is so that other people will look at us and think we're great.
Which is not the reason that Jesus came to humbly sacrificially serve us.
And this is the primary invitation, the general direction for a humble life is to not try to impress others,
but to humbly serve others.
And I just think humility is one of those things that like has to actively, intentionally be pursued every day.
It's a lifelong process.
We never get good at humility.
Like it's just we get a little bit better at it day in and day out, but we have to prioritize it because if not, it flips away.
I was listening to a sermon this week about humility and the guy pointed out something that was super convicting.
I just love being convicted.
Don't you guys love being convicted?
He said, maybe you're not sure if you really struggle with this whole pride thing.
He said, if you're ever in a room, like in a party, in a group of people,
and you notice that somebody else is trying to draw attention to themselves, and you're frustrated by that in any way,
you're probably prideful.
He's like, you're probably thinking, why does he or she get to be the center of attention?
Can't everybody tell that they're telling a one-up everybody else's stories?
They're trying to make this thing about them.
And humble people don't think that way.
Because humble people are too busy trying to sacrificially serve other people, but prideful people pay attention.
And they say, that guy's being prideful.
That girl's being prideful.
She's trying to be the center of attention when in reality, you're just frustrated.
I'm just frustrated that I'm not the center of attention.
So we're called to humbly, sacrificially serve other people, to treat other people better than ourselves,
to not try and impress people.
What are the core attitudes or ideas that get in the way of this?
Like, what gets in the way of true humility?
Well, I think as I was wrestling with this, I came up with three general ideas that I think really get in the way of humility.
And Jesus calls them out in his life when he's interacting with his disciples and with other people that are seeking to follow him.
The first, I would say, is wealth.
Wealth often gets in the way of humbly, sacrificially serving other people.
There's a guy that's interested in following Jesus in Mark chapter 10, verses 21 through 23.
And he comes and he asks Jesus, like, what does it look like to follow God?
And he's like, hey, love the Lord your God with all your heart, soul, mind, and strength.
Love your neighbor as yourself.
And the guy's like, dude, I'd do that.
Jesus is like, great.
And he says this, looking at the man, Jesus felt genuine love for him.
And he says this, there's still one thing that you haven't done.
Go and sell all of your possessions and give the money to the poor and you will have treasures in heaven.
Then come and follow me.
At this, the man's face fell and he went away sad, for he had many possessions.
Jesus looked around and said to his disciples, how hard is it for the rich man to enter the kingdom of God?
See, one major obstacle to building, to assembling our lives with an attitude of humility is his pursuit of wealth.
And often it's done out of an attitude of self-preservation, to build up our own kingdom, to have enough, to just provide for ourselves in a way that makes us feel comfortable,
in a way that we don't have to fully rely or trust on God.
We build up extra wealth that could be used to serve others, but it makes us comfortable sitting in our savings accounts.
And that's what this guy was struggling with.
He had far more than enough than he needed.
And Jesus said, this is an obstacle for you.
This is keeping you from genuinely following me.
This is keeping you from humbly, sacrificially serving other people.
And here's the thing with wealth.
Like, just being wealthy isn't in and of itself a sin.
And having wealth isn't in and of itself going to keep you from being humble.
I have met many people that are very wealthy, but that use their wealth as a resource to sacrificially serve other people.
It can be a tool to be humble.
It can be a tool to sacrificially serve other people.
But it can also be a thing that we pursue with all of our time and energy and resources.
We're far too concerned about creating side hustle jobs to get more and more money for ourselves, to store up more and more,
when in reality, like, all the attitude that comes from that is just, how can I get more?
How can I serve myself more?
And this gets a humility.
The second obstacle is reputation, status, like having people think that we're awesome.
In Jesus' disciples in Mark chapter 10, verses 35 to 38, it says,
Then James and John, the sons of Zebedee, they came over and they spoke to Jesus.
They said, Teacher, we want you to do us a favor.
Have you guys ever come to Jesus and said, Can you do me a favor?
Have you ever been there?
Maybe.
I have a couple times.
We want you to do us a favor.
Jesus said, What is your request?
They replied, When you sit in your glorious throne, we want to sit in the places of honor next to you,
one on your right and one on your left.
The other ten disciples found out about this, and they were mad.
So Jesus called them all together, and he said, The rulers of this world, they lorded over their people.
They used their status, their reputation as a leader to inflict this negative consequence on other people.
Officials, they flaunt their authority over those under them.
But among you, among Christians, among followers of Jesus, among those people of the kingdom of God, it will be different.
Whoever wants to be a leader among you must be your servant, and whoever wants to be first among you must be the slave of everyone else.
For even the Son of Man came not to be served, but to serve others and to give his life a ransom for many.
So often, we don't sacrificially serve others.
We don't have humility because we're trying to build up a reputation for ourselves.
We use our time and our energy and our resources and our interactions with other people to puff ourselves up,
to try and create this persona where people think we're great.
And this is what James and John were doing.
They were following Jesus.
They were doing the right thing, right?
Like, they gave up a lot to follow Jesus, but then they got distracted and they thought, Jesus is famous, and we want to be famous, too.
Like, we want this status that comes with being famous.
And we gave up so much.
We deserve this.
How often do we fall into the same trap, trying to build a reputation for ourselves?
We gave up a lot to follow Jesus.
It would be nice if I had this great reputation of people around me, if people thought I was an awesome Christian,
if people thought I was a great mom, a great dad, if I had this status where people looked at me and wanted my wisdom and my resources.
Reputation gets in the way of humility.
I found out this week as I was studying that the most asked question of Jesus in the Gospels is, who is the greatest?
Like, people just kept asking this question.
Reputation is something that's at the central idea of our hearts.
And Jesus attacked the attitude that his disciples had about reputation in the Lord's Supper, in John chapter 13.
See, Jesus was in charge of creating the preparations for the Last Supper.
He sent his disciples ahead.
He's like, hey, I've got it taken care of.
Go to this place.
They'll take you up to this room.
Take care of it.
Set it all up.
Right?
And the person who was in charge of setting something up, like setting that meal up, would have also been in charge of getting a servant to wash the feet of the people that walked in for the meal.
Jesus intentionally didn't do that.
Because he wanted to see what his followers would do.
They'd been with him for three years, washing his life.
He wanted to see how they learned their lessons.
They understand that this thing is all about humble sacrifice, selflessly serving other people.
They file in one by one, jockeying for the best seat of the table, trying to make sure that the other disciples knew that Jesus liked them better, that they were more successful at this discipling thing.
And as they were jockeying for positions, trying to build reputation and status for themselves, the creator of the universe got down on his hands and knees and started to wash their feet.
Looked them in the eye, covered in dust, dirt, feces, washed their feet.
And then he gets to Peter, and all of us love Peter, right?
Because he makes us feel better about ourselves sometimes.
And he's washing Peter's feet, and Peter goes, no, wash everything.
Give me a bath.
And I think the attitude there is this false humility, this false reputation, right?
It's like, let me be, I'm so good at this thing.
Like, man, we just get so distracted by trying to build status and reputation for ourselves when the one that we're following gets down on his hands and knees to wash his feet.
The last thing that distracts us from humility is strength.
Jesus is about to go to the cross.
He gets arrested.
And in Mark 14, 46 and 47, it says, the others grabbed Jesus and arrested him.
But one man, again, Peter, thanks for making us feel better about ourselves.
He pulled out his sword, and he struck the high priest's sleigh, flashing off his ear.
We try and overcome this attitude of selflessly sacrificing.
Jesus is on his way to selflessly sacrifice for you, for me, for his disciples, for the people who are arresting him.
It's all about humble sacrifice.
And instead, we're like, no, this shouldn't happen.
We need to take control.
We need to use our strength, our power, our resources, whatever we have to fight back against rather than to selflessly serve.
And Jesus, time and time again, sacrificially serves, lays down his privileges, his resources, his life to serve us.
I love this quote from F.B. Meyer.
He says, I used to think that God's gifts were on shelves, one above another.
As the taller we grow, the easier we can reach them.
But now I find that God's gifts are on shelves, and the lower we stoop, the more that we get.
See, the disciples, the ones that gave up everything to follow Jesus, they're in the position that we are, right?
Like, the decision that we made, for those of you that are followers of Jesus, like, you decided to give up your own privileges, your own desires, your own wants, and your own needs to follow after Jesus.
You're in the same position as the disciples.
And as they were following Jesus, they got distracted, and they thought, let me get better at this thing.
Let me grow up higher at this thing.
Let me climb this ladder.
And Jesus constantly pushed them to walk down the ladder, not up the ladder.
And it flies in the face of the American ideology.
The American ideology is all about climbing the ladder of wealth, status, and strength and power.
It's all about climbing up.
And the kingdom of God is all about climbing down.
We naturally don't congregate at the bottom of the shelf.
We tend to reject humility, or we fake humility to climb the ladder.
Paul's instructions for successful Christian life and church go directly in the face of some of our deepest desires for wealth and status and strength.
So just in case we were going to get confused by Paul's instructions and make excuses for not always sacrificially serving others,
he gives us this picture, this tutorial video of Jesus doing it perfectly.
Verses 5 through 8.
It says,
This passage preaches for itself.
I'm going to try and stay all the way.
Instead, he gave up.
Jesus gave up his divine privileges.
He took a humble position of a slave and was born a human being.
And when he appeared in human form, he humbled himself in obedience to God and died a criminal's death on the cross.
Paul says,
Do you want to know what humility looks like?
Do you want to know how to live out humility perfectly?
Do what Jesus did.
Have the same mind that Jesus had.
If we're going to grow in the attitude of humility, it starts and ends with daily looking at Jesus.
Essentially, these are lyrics of a worship song that the early church was singing to remind themselves of all that Jesus had done for them,
of his humility from his birth to his exaltation.
See, I love where this starts.
It starts with his incarnation.
It starts with his birth.
And honestly, most of us, as we think about the humility of Jesus, we tend to rush to the cross.
Like 95% of the year we think about the cross, except for like December.
And then we think about baby Jesus in the manger.
December, and when we watch, what's that movie?
Will Ferrell, baby Jesus.
Oh, they're good nights.
We wouldn't do that, though.
We would not do that.
None of us have ever done that.
Okay.
We tend to rush to the cross, but Paul's passage here starts with the incarnation.
Coming to earth to be born of a human was all about sacrificial service.
It was all about humility.
Jesus came in a little-known town called Bethlehem.
He sacrificed everything.
He laid down his equality with God to be born a human being.
Diapers, learning to walk, learning to talk.
The creator of the universe went through puberty.
Puberty!
For you and for me.
That's humility.
That's sacrifice.
His incarnation.
Humility.
Every moment of his life, from his incarnation to his brutal death on the cross, and let's not lose track of the sight that Romans didn't kill people on the cross because it was effective, because it was efficient, because it was a cost-effective way to kill people.
They did it to humiliate the person being killed.
It's the most humiliating death that anybody could ever have experienced, and from his incarnation, from his birth and his life to his death on the Roman cross, it was all humility.
He did it to serve you and to serve me.
I love how Andrew Murray puts it.
He says,
Humility is the chief characteristic that is the root and essence of Christ's character as our Redeemer.
What is his incarnation but his heavenly humility?
What is his life but his earthly humility?
And what is his atonement but humility?
He humbled himself and became obedient to death.
And what is his ascension and his glory but humility exalted?
He humbled himself.
Therefore, God exalted him to the highest place in heaven where he was one with the Father in his birth, in his life, and in his death on the earth, and in his return to the right hand of the Father.
It is all humility.
From his birth, to his life, to his death, to his resurrection and ascension, it was all about sacrificially loving and serving us.
And notice how in this passage, Jesus gives up the three things that we tend to struggle with when it comes to humility.
He gives up his reputation in verse 6.
Though he was God, he did not think of equality with God as something to cling to.
He gave up his status at sitting at the right hand of the Father as creator of the universe.
He literally gave up his reputation to be born a no-name, a carpenter that nobody knew or cared about, to live 30 years of his life in obscurity, humility.
He gave up his reputation.
He gave up his wealth.
In verse 7, instead, he gave up his divine privileges.
He sat on the throne with every resource and everything that was created on earth, under the earth.
He had everything, and he gave it all up.
Isaiah says that he was a homeless person, nothing special to look at.
He gave all of his divine privileges, his wealth, his reputation to come, and to not even know where he was going to lay his head at night.
Humility.
And lastly, he gave up his strength when he's about to be taken to the cross, and Peter's chopping off people's ears, fighting back with his strength.
Jesus says, don't you know I could have called down legions of angels?
I'm not doing this because I can't win the fight.
I'm not doing this because I'm not strong enough.
I'm doing this out of humility, out of sacrificial love.
I have all the strength I need to overcome this fight.
Christ's willingness to submit himself to this level of humility is rooted, this is good, is rooted in his trusting in the good character of God the Father.
Christ, you know, see, oftentimes, oftentimes we run away from the idea of humility out of self-preservation.
If we're always sacrificially serving other people, then who's going to serve us?
Where are we going to get our stuff from?
Where's our food and our family's provision going to come from?
And Jesus, he knew.
He trusted the good character of the Father.
He knew that God would reward his humility with exaltation and the exaltation of others.
Our attitude of humility comes from trusting the good character of God,
knowing that as we sacrificially serve other people, that God will provide, that he will take care of us,
that he's already given us everything we need in Christ.
So we've wrestled with the instructions.
I've seen the picture of Jesus do it perfectly.
What's the end result?
If we step back and look at a life in a church that is built on the attitude,
assembled on the attitude of humility, what's the final product?
Verse 9,
Lastly, Paul paints a vivid picture for us of what the end result of Christ's perfect humility is.
See, God is faithful to his promises that humility and sacrificial love is rewarded in his kingdom.
This is the economy of the kingdom of God, humility and sacrificial love.
And because Jesus gave the ultimate picture of humility and sacrificial love,
the greatest demonstration of humility was resulted with the greatest exaltation.
Jesus is sitting at the right hand of the Father, making his enemies a footstool.
One day he will return and set everything as it was designed to be and every knee will bow and tongue will confess that Christ Jesus is Lord.
If you're here and you're a skeptic or a deep thinker, you might be asking yourself, okay, cool.
Jesus is the greatest example of humility ever.
If he's so humble, then why does this whole thing end with him sitting on a throne demanding that everybody bow down?
That doesn't sound like humility, right?
If you're thinking that at all, or if you weren't, and now I introduced that thought into your mind.
I'm sorry.
But people have wrestled with this.
Skeptics and deep thinkers have wrestled with this idea for a long time.
You wouldn't be the first person to struggle with this question.
And I really like how John Piper succinctly answers this question.
He says this.
He says,
Oh, how we need people to see that Christ's not comfort is their all-satisfying and everlasting treasure.
Magnifying the supremacy of God in all things is the essence of God's love, his humble love.
The supremacy of God's glory is the source and sum of full and lasting joy.
Essentially, the answer to this question is God is the only being that exists that can express sacrificial love and pointing others back to himself.
He's the only being who is humble by pointing others to himself because in himself is where they receive full and lasting joy.
If humility is sacrificially serving other people, then God, by pointing us to his son Jesus, is sacrificially serving us.
He's laying down his life to point us to the one thing that brings us full and everlasting joy.
This is our invitation to humble ourselves before God, to assemble our lives according to the instructions that he has given us.
See, we go back to our illustration of assembling something, sometimes using the wrong parts to make it happen.
Those of us that are in here that are followers of Jesus, we know, we can make it work.
We can live a somewhat Christian life, putting priorities in the wrong places, and just overemphasizing things that we shouldn't and underemphasizing things that we should.
We know we can make it work.
We can piece together this thing.
We can make it work.
We know we can make it work.
This is our invitation to orient our life, to assemble our life the way that God designed it to be.
Jesus showed us perfectly what that looks like, always humbly, sacrificially serving others.
Humility is rarely glamorous, and it often leads us to the cross.
But it's the starting point for a successful Christian life in church.
If you're here and you're not a follower of Jesus, again, I'm not one of those preachers that's going to say your life's going to be terrible.
You're going to be trapped in sin, and you're never going to have any fun, and life's never going to be good for you.
Like, no, you can piece it together.
You can make it work.
But it's not as you were designed to be.
You were designed to be bowed down before the foot of King Jesus, trusting his good character to take care of you, to provide for you.
If all of us would align ourselves with the will of God the Father for our lives,
if we all would align ourselves by humbly, sacrificially serving our neighbor as ourselves,
what God could do with that obedience.
See, when Jesus promises abundant life, he's not promising wealth all the time, status all the time, strength, success.
He's promising fulfillment because you're living the way that you were designed to live,
in right relationship with God, in right relationship with one another.
If you're here and you've been told that following Jesus is just about praying a prayer, raising your hand, and then not changing anything about your life.
I think that's kind of a misplaced understanding of the gospel.
I'm not saying that faith in Jesus alone doesn't save you because it does.
But true joy, true success as a follower of Jesus comes when we align ourselves with the way of Jesus.
Humble sacrifice.
Climbing down the ladder to love and serve our neighbor as ourself.
And it flies in the face of what we naturally want to do.
So what's our response?
Will we spend our lives trying to climb the ladder to the top only to realize that it's not exactly what we thought it would be?
Have you ever been there?
Have you ever get the bonus check for the amount of money that you thought would make you feel content and satisfied?
Realize that you need to have another zero on the end to really satisfy you?
Have you ever get that position at work that you thought, if you got it, that that's when you would really feel like a success,
when you would really feel like a grown-up, when you really feel like you were doing it?
You went back to work next Monday and still kind of felt like failure?
See, the enemy promises and lies to us that if we get all of these things, if we climb up to the top of the ladder,
then we'll be successful and satisfied and everything will be great.
But any of us who have tried it, we realize we get to the top and it's not what we thought it would be.
Because true, abundant life happens at the bottom of the ladder.
It happens with Jesus.
See, successful life, a fulfilled life, a satisfied life is all about being close to Jesus.
Proximity to Jesus brings fullness of joy and Jesus doesn't find himself at the top of the ladder.
He's always at the bottom.
Successful Christian life and church is assembled with the attitude of humility.
I want to end our time together by looking at one verse in the book of John.
John the Baptist was the forerunner for Jesus, going ahead of Jesus, pointing people to Jesus.
Jesus actually said John was the greatest man born of a woman.
So if we want us to think about what does it look like to successfully follow Jesus?
Jesus said John the Baptist, he's crushing it.
Look at him.
And what was his life built on?
What was the attitude that John had?
Well, as Christ's ministry was gaining success, people are leaving John to follow Jesus.
His disciples are looking around as the crowd is getting smaller and they go,
Hey John, all of our donations are getting smaller.
The strength and energy of our movement that was building is going away and it's all shifting to the sky.
Jesus, what should we do about that?
This is John's response in John 3 verse 30.
He said, I am filled with joy at Christ's success.
He must become greater and greater and I must become less and less.
This is my prayer for you.
This is my prayer for me.
This is my prayer for your family and my family and our church and this city, our nation and this world that people, individuals would come to realize.
The same thing that John realized, that true joy comes from Christ's success.
His exaltation, us bowing down at the foot of Jesus is where true success comes.
May he become greater and greater.
May we become less and less.
Let's pray.
Father, humility is not a natural posture of my heart.
Sacrificially serving others is something that I enjoy doing on occasion when it fits my agenda.
Father, you sent Jesus to show us what true humility, true sacrificial love looks like.
And you've called us to have that same attitude and that starts with sacrifice, with me saying no to things that I want in order to say yes to things that are better.
God, may we be a people that trust your good character, that know that laying down our own privileges, our preferences, our desires, that it will ultimately be rewarded with the one thing that our heart wants more than anything.
And that is the exaltation of Jesus to the throne of our hearts, our lives, and this world.
Jesus, may you become greater and greater.
May we become less and less.
For your glory and our good.
In Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
We're going to take communion.